# Dan Zeng

danzeng8@gmail.com | Personal website: http://www.dan-zeng.com

#### **Research Interests**

I am interested in computational geometry, computer graphics, 3D computer vision, and imaging. Currently, I develop algorithms for reconstructing topologically optimized shapes from sensor data such as image volumes and point clouds. I have experience developing end-to-end computer vision and graphics software pipelines. I am interested in augmented/virtual reality, autonomous driving, gaming, and related applications.

#### **Education**

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science (Advisor: Dr. Tao Ju) Bachelor of Science in Computer Science (Wash U.) Washington University in St. Louis August 2017-May 2022 (expected) August 2013-May 2017 Saint Louis, MO

### Research Experience

## Graph-based optimization for topological simplification of 3D shapes

2019-present

Collaboration: Wash U., Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, and St. Louis University

- Developed a novel global optimization algorithm for maximally simplifying topological noise within a 3D shape with minimal changes to its geometry. The algorithm optimally selects cuts and fills via reduction to a Node-Weighted Steiner Tree problem.
- The algorithm shows vastly improved topological and geometric results compared to prior methods, achieving the optimal topological result in nearly all cases and achieving >99.9% simplification for very complex examples (e.g. corn roots from CT scans) with thousands of noisy topological features.
- Paper "To cut or to fill: A global optimization approach to topological simplification" was accepted and presented at SIGGRAPH Asia 2020. Project page: <a href="https://danzeng8.github.io/topo-simplifier/">https://danzeng8.github.io/topo-simplifier/</a>

Geometric algorithms for computing root system architecture from X-ray CT imaging 2020-present Collaboration: Wash U., Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, and St. Louis University

- Developed TopoRoot, a method for computing hierarchy and fine-grained traits of maize roots from CT images. The method repairs topological errors, creates a geometric graph to represent branching structure, and infers the hierarchy using an algorithm which minimizes the maximum hierarchy level.
- TopoRoot computes fine-grained traits with vastly improved accuracy (up to 380% improvement depending on trait, see paper for details) compared to prior methods, and also computes novel traits.
- TopoRoot runs within 7 minutes for 400<sup>3</sup> images, enabling high-throughput computation.
- Demonstrated usefulness to biological studies through the ability to differentiate between a mutant variety of Maize and a wild-type across 12 of 23 fine-grained traits which are computed by TopoRoot.
- Paper under review by Plant Methods journal. Preprint: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457522">https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457522</a>, Github: <a href="https://github.com/danzeng8/TopoRoot">https://github.com/danzeng8/TopoRoot</a>
- Lead the project forward through clear communication with plant biologists and computer scientists.

#### Facebook Reality Labs Research Internship: A robust domestic UV mapping tool May-Sept. 2020

- Developed a tool which uses Variational Shape Approximation to compute charts and Least Squares Conformal Maps to flatten them in order to produce UV maps free of non-manifold artifacts.
- Integrated the tool into the existing mesh reconstruction pipeline. The tool showed an ability to simplify the pipeline, which previously required external tools with specialized knowledge to operate.
- On a dataset of highly complex indoor reconstructions, the tool showed 50% lower parameterization error (reducing the visual distortion) and >20x speed-up compared to open-source implementations.

Collaboration: Wash U., Donald Danforth Plant Science Center, and St. Louis University

- Developed a method to trace the primary branches of sorghum panicles as part of a study which revealed continuous morphological variation across genetically diverse sorghum panicles. The method first computes a geometric skeleton graph from the X-ray CT image, then traverses the graph to identify primary branches. Github: https://bit.ly/37DxkWQ
- The traits derived from each computed branch showed high correlation with hand measurements.
- Published in and on the cover of New Phytologist journal, May 2020 (cover: <a href="https://bit.ly/2UitFL6">https://bit.ly/2UitFL6</a>)
- Wash U news article highlighting my contributions: <a href="https://bit.ly/2VQ0rDR">https://bit.ly/2VQ0rDR</a>

#### Danforth Plant Science Center Research Internship: Christopher Topp's Lab May-August 2018

- Researched geometric methods for phenotyping plant roots and panicles. My observations and discussions with biologists formed the foundation for some of the above works.
- Prototyped a semi-automatic software pipeline for analyzing X-ray CT imaging of plants and mentored lab members on its usage on lab machines.
- Generated surface reconstructions of plant structures from point clouds and voxelized image volumes for educational virtual reality exhibits.

#### Geometric Algorithms for Modeling Protein Structures

2016-2017

- Implemented a C++ interface for pathwalking (algorithm for determining protein backbones in Cryo-EM density maps) in Gorgon, a molecular modeling software suite (<a href="https://bit.ly/2VZVbNG">https://bit.ly/2VZVbNG</a>)
- Developed a method that uses local maxima to identify  $\alpha$ -helices and  $\beta$ -sheets in density maps.
- Presented at Wash. U.'s Undergraduate Research Symposium (poster: <a href="https://bit.ly/3jQxiAE">https://bit.ly/3jQxiAE</a>)

#### **Publications**

- Dan Zeng, Yiwen Ju, Mao Li, Ni Jiang, Hannah Schreiber, Erin Chambers, David Letscher, Tao Ju, Christopher N. Topp. 2021. TopoRoot: A method for computing hierarchy and fine-grained traits of maize roots from X-ray CT images. Plant Methods (under review). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457522">https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.08.24.457522</a>
- David Letscher, Erin W. Chambers, Tao Ju, Hannah Schreiber, Dan Zeng. 2021. VHS: a package for homological simplification of voxelized plant root data for skeletonization. Currently under review by Computational Geometry: Theory and Applications.
- Dan Zeng, Erin Chambers, David Letscher, Tao Ju. 2020. To cut or to fill: A global optimization approach to topological simplification. ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. ACM Siggraph Asia 2020), 39(6): No. 201. https://doi.org/10.1145/3414685.3417854
- Mao Li, Mon-Ray Shao, Dan Zeng, Tao Ju, Elizabeth A. Kellogg, Christopher N. Topp. 2020.
   Comprehensive 3D Phenotyping reveals Continuous Morphological Variation across Genetically
   Diverse Sorghum Inflorescences. New Phytologist Journal. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.16533">https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.16533</a>

#### Honors / Awards

- Imaging Sciences Pathway Fellowship (2019-2021), awarded by the Division of Biology and Biomedical Sciences at Washington University
- Dean's Select PhD Fellowship at Washington University (2017)
- Thomas H. Eliot Scholarship Award at Washington University (2013)

# **Teaching Assistant Experience**

CSE 554 Geometric Computing for Biomedicine (2 lectures given, office hours), CSE 530 Database Management Systems (office hours) , CSE 132 Introduction to Computer Science II (office hours)

#### **Technical Skills**

- Programming Languages and Libraries: C/C++(Expert), Python(Expert), Mathematica(Expert), Java(Proficient), Matlab(Proficient), OpenGL, CGAL, Eigen, Boost, TBB, NumPy
- Other Professional Skills / Tools: Visual Studio, Visual Studio Code, Git, Vim, Adobe Photoshop & Premiere, HTML/CSS, Javascript, R, UCSF Chimera, 3D Vision, Machine learning model building
- Languages: English (native), Chinese (fluent)

#### **References**

### Tao Ju

Professor at Washington University in St. Louis, Department of Computer Science and Engineering Vice Dean of Research at School of Engineering & Applied Science

Email: taoju@wustl.edu

#### **Erin Chambers**

Professor at Saint Louis University, Department of Computer Science and Engineering Associate Chair

Email: erin.chambers@slu.edu

#### **Christopher Topp**

Principal Investigator, Donald Danforth Plant Science Center

Email: ctopp@danforthcenter.org